Sigma Xi, Indiana University Chapter records, 1904-1974 C186
Indiana University Archives
Sigma Xi, Indiana University Chapter records
1904-1974
Indiana University Archives
Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. Indiana University Chapter
C186
1.4 cubic feet 2 boxes
Founded in 1886 as an honorary society for science and engineering, today Sigma Xi is an international research society that strives to promote the health of the scientific enterprise and honor scientific achievement. The Indiana University chapter of Sigma Xi was chartered in 1904. The collection consists of nomination forms, minutes, correspondence, by-laws, and constitutions. Also included is a report drawn up circa 1974 entitled "Indiana University chapter: the Society of Sigma Xi, 1904-1974."
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Historical Note
Founded in 1886 as an honorary society for science and engineering, today Sigma Xi is an international research society that strives to promote the health of the scientific enterprise and honor scientific achievement. With more than 500 chapters at colleges and universities, industrial research centers, and government laboratories, the Society boasts nearly 75,000 members worldwide.
The Sigma Xi Indiana University chapter was chartered in 1904. The first officers were William Lowe Bryan, President (also president of the university), Arthur L. Foley, Vice-President, David M. Mottier, Treasurer and Edgar R. Cumings and Joshua W. Beede were named Recording Secretary and Corresponding Secretary, respectively. Throughout the years, a number of prominent IU faculty members either held officer positions or memberships in Sigma Xi, including Fernandus Payne, Alfred C. Kinsey, and Sid Robinson.
Sigma Xi is still active at IU.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Nominations, Minutes, and Administrative records.
Scope and Content Note
While a small collection, consisting of only 1.4 cubic ft., the Sigma Xi records still hold a wealth of information for the researcher interested in the Society at Indiana University.
The first series, Nominations, consists of individual nominations to the Society from the time of its inception to 1938. Nomination forms include candidate information such as degrees, status at IU, and qualifications for membership.
The Minutes series, 1904-1972, is surprisingly complete. In addition to the meeting minutes, the Secretary also sometimes included correspondence and flyers about Society events.
The final series, Administrative records, 1904-1974, includes by-laws, constitutions, secretary correspondence, and member information. Also found is a history drawn up circa 1974 entitled "Indiana University Chapter: The Society of Sigma Xi, 1904-1974."
Acquisition Information
Accession 0530.
Learned institutions and societies --Indiana --Bloomington --Records and correspondence.; Learned institutions and societies --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Learned institutions and societies --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Indiana University chapter: the Society of Sigma Xi, 1904-1974.; Universities and colleges -- Societies, etc.; Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. Indiana University Chapter; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Indiana University -- students -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. Indiana University Chapter -- Archives; Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. Indiana University Chapter -- Records and correspondence
- Nominations, 1904-1938 (Box 1)
  - First after charter?, Dec 1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905-1938 (Box 1)
    - A-C (Box 1)
    - D-E (Box 1)
    - F-I (Box 1)
    - J-O (Box 1)
    - P-S (Box 1)
    - T-Z (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1904-1972
  - Minutes (Box 1)
    - 1904-1916 (Box 1)
    - 1921-1936 (Box 1)
    - 1936-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1972 (Box 1)
- Administrative records, 1906-1974 (Box 2)
  - List of Officers and Members and Program of Sigma Xi -- Indiana Chapter for, 1906-1910 (Box 2)
  - Chapter statistics report, 1915-1922 (Box 2)
  - By-laws, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Constitution and registration book, 1904-1967 (Box 2)
  - History of the Indiana University Chapter: The Society of Sigma Xi, 1904-1974 (Box 2)
  - Corresponding Secretary Letters and Answers, 1904-1914 (Box 2)